Okay, so,
the title of your book is called am I Bipolar
or Waking Up? Speaker 1 Hang on, hang on. That's
the. Speaker 2 First book. The first book.
Okay. Speaker 1 Or second, because I'm waking
up. Second book is bipolar Awakenings. Okay, okay.
So maybe we talk about both books. We've got some
time. Yeah, but yeah, the second book, Bipolar
Awakenings, will have more implications for your
listeners. Speaker 2 Okay. Okay. Speaker 1 So we
can start with my bipolar waking up. It's a good
place to start. Speaker 2 I mean, I think it's
probably all going to weave into each other. Where
I would like to start is I would like to bring
in. So say somebody is tuning in and they don't
really know much about bipolar. They don't they,
you know, maybe we've heard this term and maybe
they've heard of someone who's been bipolar. Maybe
the most they know about bipolar is someone who's
like, well, I don't know. Speaker 2 They seem
really happy. And and suddenly they're really
ticked off, you know, the very, thin, explanation
of bipolar. So can you tell me? I guess let's
just start with what what is bipolar for someone
who's who's just learning this. Speaker 1 Okay. So
bipolar disorder is like all mental disorders
in the big book of Mental Disorders, the DSM
Diagnostic Statistical Manual. It's a label given
to a set of symptoms. Okay. So there's no actual
disease there that they can find biologically.
Okay. There's just a set of symptoms. And what
most people think of as bipolar disorder, they
would label bipolar two which goes hypomania
and depression. Speaker 1 So what's hypomania.
Hypomania tends to be symptoms like not sleeping
very well nonstop or intense incessant speech. A
lot of business ideas sometimes hyper sexuality,
sometimes some hyper aggressiveness. And it just
kind of feels like for the outsider, it just feels
like you're just dealing with it. Extremely
difficult person. Okay. And that's the mania
side of things. Speaker 1 Spending lots of money,
bad investments, these kind of things too. Then it
flips to the depression. Okay, so you've got this
high lots of energy spending less money to do all
these activities, driving everybody crazy. And
then there's the depression side where everybody
calms down. But you're miserable, right? So that's
bipolar two. Bipolar one is when that hypomania
goes into psychosis and you have a complete break
with reality, and you enter a space where you kind
of feel like you're dreaming, right. Speaker 1 And
back in the 80s, that usually is labeled anybody
back in the 80s who got acute psychosis, it would
have been labeled schizophrenia. But somehow along
the way, the labels got shifted around. And most
people going into acute psychosis today get the
label of bipolar one. So bipolar one with
psychosis, bipolar two, just the hypomania.
And then both have the depression on the other
side okay. Speaker 2 And so so that's the the
definition as broadly as the culture. Speaker 1
No clinical thing. Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. Okay.
And then what I mean you seem to have discovered
different definitions or you know, you seem to
have expanded more on it. So I guess what would be
kind of your definitions. Speaker 1 Yeah. So well,
there's it's not so much, that I disagree with
that definition. Like if somebody has those
symptoms, I'm like, okay, this guy's in that
bipolar space for sure. For sure. But, what are
the roots is the big difference. And according to
psychiatry, the roots are biological. And like all
the DSM diagnoses, they they tend to say that it's
either genetic and then they point to too much or
too little dopamine or serotonin. Speaker 1 But
the science shows that and this comes from, Robert
Whittaker. He's, a writer for The Boston Globe who
was taken on this mission. He has a website, Mad
in america.com. And what the science shows is that
the range of serotonin and dopamine are the same
for people with mental disorders as they are for
normal people. So there well, there is biological
shifts happening. Speaker 1 There is no inherent
genetic basis for a mental disorder. You know,
and then actual mental illnesses that take
place usually involve memory loss, things like
Alzheimer's, dementia, these kind of things. You
have problems in remembering things. Okay. Mental
disorders don't take you or mental illness
doesn't take you in the non ordinary states
of consciousness per se. Speaker 1 All right.
Like what you go into in psychosis okay. So,
my perception in talking to people and I have
to go back to my own experience for this. But
what I believe and how I practice things is that,
mental disorders, particularly bipolar disorder,
schizophrenia, because there's a lot of gray area
between those two and depression have roots in
trauma, and that the trauma is somehow lodged in
our inherent bioenergetics system. Speaker 1 Now
in the East, they could call the system the
chakra system, or maybe the Kundalini system,
subtle body. Kundalini is like your life force
energy in China. They might call it G or qigong.
You might have heard qigong that the G and qigong.
So you've got this life force coming through you.
And then there's these blockages rooted in trauma.
Speaker 1 And when those blockages become too
much, then that can cause a non ordinary state
experience. You know, like going into psychosis,
you know, but the roots of depression are the same
and that kind of thing. And then when you go into
these non ordinary state experiences there's only
about 13 very spiritual delusions that pop up and
that's it. Speaker 1 There's like 13 of them. And
then there's if, if a lot of fear comes over you,
there's also paranoia that can creep in too. And
hallucinations are part of this as well, sometimes
with more severe situations. But for the most
part, we're talking about 13 delusions that are
obviously very spiritual. Okay. Speaker 2 So you
said obviously very spiritual. One thing I found,
for my personal experience, was it took me a
while to even let words like spiritual into
my vocabulary. I didn't consider myself so much
spiritual. And so, like any any of that stuff,
I kind of just had a, it's not really for me.
And it took me a while to kind of actually start
comprehending those, I'm completely different
place now. Speaker 2 This is many years ago, but,
could you. I'm just thinking of someone who's
listening. Maybe they've experienced some sort
of bipolar things and they have someone in their
life. Maybe they're in that same boat that I was
in years ago. Could you maybe expand more on
the word spiritual? What might that mean to.
Speaker 1 Okay, okay. Well, yeah. And according
to Ken Wilber, there are 12 different, definitions
for spiritual or spirituality. So when one person
speaks about spiritual or spiritual things,
it can be interpreted completely differently
than somebody else, you know? So there's a
lot of confusion around that topic. But, just to
get very practical and tangible when I'm talking
about spiritual delusions, and I and I made a
video about this on YouTube, my most popular
video from years ago was called Why You Think Your
Jesus. Speaker 1 People go into bipolar disorder
and they think that they are in psychosis. They
think they are either the reincarnation of Jesus
giving birth to Jesus through a messiah. They're
Buddha. There's some sort of figure here to save
the world, you know? And so that's like one of the
strongest delusions that that happen. You know,
it's like so it's like of the sort of otherworldly
domain you, you might say. Speaker 1 And what I
see in that case is people getting in touch
with the divine within themselves, you know,
now, conversely, also spiritual. And often these
days people don't think of it as spiritual. You
can also have a demonic side to this whole
thing. It tends to be projected most of the
time, like it's because it's more fear
oriented. Speaker 1 But you can think,
often like the devil or demons are after you.
It can manifest as aliens that are kind of evil
aliens kind of following me around or performing
a surgery on me or something like that. And,
or you can even think that you're the devil, and
some people think that they'll tell me that they
thought they were the Jesus one minute and the
devil the next. Speaker 1 And because what's going
on is the energies are kind of flipping inside
of you. You're getting in touch with one, and
then it turns and gets in touch with the others.
Because in this state, your ego has breaking down,
broken down, and your psyche is just running free
rein without control. You know, you've really got
no control in that situation. Speaker 1 Yeah.
Speaker 2 Yeah, yeah, it makes me think of,
are you familiar with Ram Dass, the spiritual
teacher? Sure, sure. Yeah. He has this story
where he tells, essentially he had a brother, and
his brother was, actually in, like, a psychiatric
ward, and he would visit his brother and he
would talk about, his brother was was in that
same position. Speaker 2 He was he thought he was
Jesus. Like, he would just at all times. And it's
funny rundown to talk about, you know, here I am
is this person I've been in, in Nepal, in India,
and I'm where I got a beard and I had these mala
beads and I'm wearing, like, robes essentially,
you know, I look more like Jesus and my brother
does, and he sanely goes to visit his brother and,
him and his brother getting some sort of quarrel
and. Speaker 1 The. Speaker 2 Like. The final
marker that Ram Dass puts on the conversation is,
he tells his brother, like, the problem is that
you think you're Jesus. And I know that we're
all Jesus. And it's kind of this, like, it's
not necessarily about just the self. Like, there
is some truth and what you're feeling. There is
kind of this, with spirituality, you have to allow
paradox. Speaker 2 So it's not just this, like you
might, you may feel that you are having these,
you know, godlike, experiences and downloads
or whatever, but it's not that you are the one
special person out of a billion people gets these.
It's kind of like a human experience. So anyway,
around us mentions that, and I think that's,
I always thought that was a really good, teaching
on that one. Speaker 1 Right. And, and it's a
good indicator also of how severe severe is a
difficult word, but how severe the disorder is by
how attached and how concrete the interpretation
is of what the person is going through. So if you
get somebody back on medications for example, and
then they're like, I thought that I was some sort
of a Jesus figure, you know, speaking of it, sort
of abstract or vague ways, right? Speaker 1 Versus
you don't understand. I'm here to save the world,
you know, and, and that kind of person who is just
there. I am the only Messiah that Jesus is, and
you need to respect me and bow down to me. Wow.
That's a very difficult person to heal, you know,
or to help heal. But the first one who was like,
I'm pretty sure I thought it was Jesus for a
while, but now I kind of get it. Speaker 1 And,
you know, they're taking a couple of medications
and that that that person, you can help if they've
got insight into their situation. Speaker 2
Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. Okay. If you'll give me,
I would love to back up a little bit. So I heard,
an inkling earlier I was listening to you on a
podcast, and, you were talking about your one of
your first experiences into, kind of the spiritual
element in what kind of started you down this
path. Speaker 2 You were at a landmark forum in,
and you had, kind of a profound experience. Could
you break that down to me? And could you also
just bring in anybody who's new? What's landmark?
What were you doing there? What were you trying to
accomplish, any of that? Speaker 1 Sure. And just
to tell any of your listeners this story I tell
in my first book, and it's available as a free PDF
on my website. Okay. Am I being sold or are waking
up? Is that is the PDF? Speaker 2 I'll have the
link down below as well. Speaker 1 Okay, great. So
what happened to me is I was dealing with about
seven years of on again off again depression,
but I it was for me it was always around my
career, you know just struggling with my career.
But finally, someone convinced me to go take this
course, the landmark form landmark education. And
at the time, I didn't know anything about it, but
it was, rooted in something from the 70s called
East training. Speaker 1 And it's just a very
confrontational weekend where they really kind of
getting your face about, who you are, what you're
about, and how you're sabotaging your life and,
and, and really messing with you psychologically.
But because it was 150 people in the room together
energetically, it's really strong thing to like,
I was going to the bathroom and pardon my French
farting like I have never passed gas like this
in my entire life. Speaker 1 Every break we had,
I had to go into the bathroom and process
internally what the hell was going on farting
for everyone. It was really uncomfortable and I've
never had an experience like that since. Okay. So
funny. Yeah. But, and they controlled things like
they told you, you know, you had to promise you
will not go to the bathroom while we're in
session. Speaker 1 Like, you won't just get
up and walk out the door. You needed to wait for
breaks. And if you couldn't agree to that, you had
to leave the course like they wanted. Everybody on
the same page, you know? So it they created almost
like a cult like environment where you just you
need to buy in or you're out the door, you know,
second day of that course, though, they asked
us to do a meditation on our fear, and I didn't
think I felt any fear. Speaker 1 I was 30 years
old at the time, didn't think I felt any fear,
and then in the middle of this meditation, I saw
a depth gauge from my scuba diving equipment from,
Vancouver two months earlier. And I had I had had
a scuba diving accident. I lost my weight belt
about 90ft below sea level. Okay. And there was a
moment there where I'm looking at my depth gauge,
and I'm just wondering if I'm going to die before
I hit the surface. Speaker 1 You know, because
I lost my weight belt. I'm shooting up to the
surface from 90ft below. I'm just watching this
thing and I'm exhaling, wondering if I'm going to
make it to the top. You know? And I couldn't allow
myself to feel any sense of panic or fear in that
moment, because if you did and you hold held your
breath, that could create an air embolism and you
could die. Speaker 1 So I was just very relaxed.
I just stayed relaxed until I hit the surface,
you know? But then on that fear meditation,
I just had this huge punch in my chest and just
started bawling. And then all the fear came up
and I could feel everything, and I was shaking.
And they were encouraging us to go into deeper
fear imagery. Speaker 1 And I imagined myself
sort of being kidnaped and this kind of thing.
Once that was over, I, my, my senses had
completely shifted and I felt like I could there
was a sense of oneness, connection to everything
lighter. I felt like I knew things about life that
I didn't know before. Like before, I always felt
like I was missing something. Speaker 1 All of a
sudden it was okay. And then my senses sharpened
so I could see detail in curtains I couldn't
see before, smelling things I couldn't smell
before. It was just everything was more vivid,
you know? And then I got really emotional. And
this state carried on for about five days, and
it takes about 80 pages of my book. Speaker 1 And
then on the fifth day, I was still on the course,
and I came to this conclusion that I must
have died in that scuba diving accident,
because I felt so completely different that
this is what heaven feels. Yeah, I was like,
I was in the course thinking, this is what it
feels like when you die. And then all of a sudden
it was like, oh, that's what happened. Speaker
1 I'm dead. Wow. And I just thought everybody
in the room were actors that were just there to,
play a role, to help me move along in my life and
to move along to the next level. And I eventually
went into this other room, this other ballroom,
because it was all taking place in the ballroom
for this final night. Speaker 1 And I just thought
I was going there to meet God. And part of it
was taking off all my clothes. You know? And,
also, I peed on the carpet there. It was all like
a test. I had to let go of everything. So I let go
my bladder, too. And, eventually the police showed
up and I wouldn't put my clothes back on because
I thought this was part of the test. Speaker 1
And they grabbed me and put me in an ambulance
and took me to the hospital. And I still thought I
was going to Nirvana or Heaven or something. I was
trying to get to that other dimension. I was sure
it was dead. But then a couple of days after being
in the hospital, I started to realize nothing was
changing and that and my delusion actually started
to break down just by the fact that I was still
in the hospital and people weren't particularly
nice to me. Speaker 1 And I thought, well, this
is, I don't know what's going on. You know,
my family was very supportive while I was in the
hospital. They were devastated, but they were very
supportive. When I got home, I still had this
feeling like I'm having a spiritual experience.
I don't know what a mental disorder is. I don't
know what bipolar disorder is or schizophrenia,
but I had a spiritual experience. Speaker 1 And,
and part of it is the spiritual delusion, the
common one, feeling like you're dead or dying or
being reborn. You know, that's one being feeling
like you're being tested by God is another very
common one, you know? And then another common one
for people is feeling like they're on a special
mission here to save the world. Speaker 1 But I
didn't have that one because I was dead, right.
Like I was moving on. So all this happened in
1996. You know, I want to make that clear
to people in it. After I had a few months to
integrate and I had a family friend who was very
understanding and, and would listen was a great
listener. Speaker 1 She was from India, so she had
more of an open mind than some of the others. And,
once I had that time, I went back to work
in advertising, which is what I used to do,
and my life got a lot better. My salary tripled,
you know, in three years. People said they really
appreciated me on their business. Speaker 1 They
felt like I really cared. These kind of things,
you know, even while I was at that point, I wanted
to get out of the business, you know, I was I
needed to find some sort of spiritual mission,
you know, and after after being in advertising
for a year, I. Meadow, I met a Brazilian woman
on a trip to Peru. Speaker 1 I was I had a dream,
I was being called to Peru, and, I just kind of
went on a tour. There's a lot of details there,
but I met her on a tour, and, eventually we got
married and we moved to Brazil. Okay. And so then.
Then I became an English teacher here. And am I
like that much better? Speaker 1 My years as an
English teacher were probably the best years of my
life. And that that took me sort of between 2000
when I got married to 2007, you know, and but up,
up. That whole time I wasn't really involved in
this work. I, I thought that spiritual emergency
and mental disorder were two completely different
things in that period. Speaker 1 Right? Speaker
2 Right. Okay. So going into this, what was your
two questions? What was your background and
experience in kind of like a like psychosis,
bipolar like did were you familiar with even
that language. And then also did you have
how about the language of spirituality. Were you
spiritual before? Did you grow up with any sort of
like Christian background, anything like that or.
Speaker 1 Well, I, I was raised Catholic and, and
I had a strong interest in spirituality. I studied
religion in university. I was actually trying
to find the right one for its didn't end too
well, and I ended up being kind of atheistic or
agnostic, and that I broken a few years earlier,
you know, with, with a trip to Vancouver where I
started to have, like, synchronicities popping
and things like this. Speaker 1 And it sort
of opened me up to a faith in something bigger
than myself. And this happened two years before
I was in the hospital. So, one thing I forgot to
mention was that a year after my hospitalization,
I discovered the work of a guy named, Czech
psychiatrist named Stan Groff, Stanislav Groff,
and he had written a book, The Stormy Search
for the self, which talked about spiritual,
a kind of thing that looks like psychosis but is
actually spiritual in nature. Speaker 1 And if you
let it just play out, it can be very healing.
And he called that a spiritual emergency. And
I had all the details on a spiritual emergency
and, and basically, to keep it really simple,
he broke it down to if you're able to
internalize what you're going through, it
can be a breakthrough. But if you externalize it,
it's a breakdown, you know, and but he separate it
into two very different categories. Speaker 1 But
for me, coming out of that, I was like, oh, I had
a spiritual emergency. I did not have a mental
illness. And these are two very separate things,
you know, and I, I didn't even have any interest
in bipolar disorder. I didn't know anything about
mental disorders. I didn't think about them.
You know, once I was back to work, it was like,
okay, let me go live my life and find my true
calling. Speaker 1 Speaker 2 So, so did you feel,
did you. I mean, this is a hard word, but normal.
Did you feel normal afterwards? Like. Like what
was your homeostasis after this episode? Like,
do you feel like a completely different person
still kind of. Or. Speaker 1 I felt I didn't feel
normal, I felt natural, I felt a lot more natural.
And I was also a little weird. I think I would
be prone to sort of breaking social conventions
more often than not. Maybe I was always like that
a little bit, but then afterwards I was kind of a
little bit, a little bit more. Speaker 1 So I just
wasn't playing by the typical rules, you might
say. But I kind of lost interest in society to a
certain degree. For the years I was in Toronto,
after my hospitalization, on Saturday nights,
for example, I just stay home with my parents.
I had no interest in going out and socializing
that much. I felt like I had the secret, you know?
Speaker 1 Because I couldn't really share it with
anybody at work that I was just six months before
joining this ad agency. I was in the psychiatric
hospital. Speaker 2 You couldn't relate to
yourself? Speaker 1 Yeah, yeah. You know, and but
then I got interested in shamanism, kind of a new
age shamanism. And there was a few events around
Toronto. That's where I'm originally from. And
I would go to a few events here and there. And
then I got, you know, into this trip to Peru and,
and that was just a fascinating, fascinating thing
to do. Speaker 1 And my wife and I, like, I met my
wife in Peru, Leisa, and we got married and we
took a in 2000, we took a big trip through her
country of Brazil, backpacked all over the place
and went and visited shamans and, pages. They
would call them all over the Amazon and places
like that. Just seeing in Salvador, Bahia and
seeing, you know, the the descendants of slaves in
Salvador, channeling spirits, you know, channeling
African gods and stuff like that. Speaker 1 So we
I was really getting an incredible exposure to the
variety of, of experience you get in Brazil, both
from religious and spiritual perspectives. You
know, because it runs the whole gamut down there.
And, and a lot of non ordinary state experience
stuff happens with drugs and without drugs.
Right. Yeah. So it was a fascinating place to
be when you were interested in spirituality like I
was at the time. Speaker 1 Yeah. Speaker 2 And so,
so it sounds like. And you hadn't written your
first book by this point, right. Speaker 1 No
no no, no. Speaker 2 So so it sounds like.
Speaker 1 2011 2000, 2001. Yeah. Speaker 2 And
when did your book, when did your first book
come out. Speaker 1 2011. Speaker 2 Okay. So
it sounds like you were getting a lot of info
in new, you know, stories, and you're probably
learning a lot about this whole thing and about
yourself, right? Speaker 1 Yeah. And actually,
I had written about my hospitalization and given
it to a psychologist in the Toronto area just
a few years after it had happened to me, but I
never published it. I just kind of kept it in the
back burner. But then once I got into this work
about helping people, then I published it as am I
Bipolar or Waking up in 2011? Speaker 2 And so. So
how do you make that move into like, oh, I want to
start helping people. I feel that I have enough
knowledge about what happened to not only me,
but now I can help other people. How did you take
them? Speaker 1 I was other than learning my own,
learning about my own experience through the
work of Stan Groff and Ken Wilber as well. I
wasn't I was just maybe looking for a calling, but
I didn't know how to help people. I was involved
in shamanism in Brazil. Sometimes I'd work as
like a dog soldier, you know, which would be
like giving people water or something like that.
Speaker 1 That's what they called it, right? But,
in 2007, my wife's younger niece, Anna. And that's
important to point out because it wasn't genetic.
It was her niece. It wasn't mine. She went into
an experience. We just got a call out of nowhere,
and she went into experience, and her parents were
telling us what happened, and I was like, well,
that sounds like what happened to me. Speaker
1 And we went to support her through it. And it
was very close to what I had been through. And I
thought, oh, well, this is a spiritual emergency.
And I talked to the parents and tried to explain
to the parents what happened to me. I'd never told
the family what had happened to me, you know,
not that side of the family. Speaker 1 They're
very conservative. But I thought, I need to get
the fear out of that place because the fear is
what can really do damage. So I really focused
on that. And my wife would support, her niece,
but and we had good results. The psychiatrist and
psychologist both said they had never seen someone
recover so quickly. Then. Speaker 1 Then she did,
but they still gave her the meds. And I was like,
well, why are they giving you the meds? And and
then I, they said, oh, it's going to be a few
months of meds. And I was like a few months.
And then, then I got online and learned it's
going to be a lifetime of medication. Speaker 1
And that's where I just went. What the hell are
we talking about here? You know, it was just
totally new news to me, you know? And then I
started to go deeper and I started ordering
books on Amazon and discovered that actually,
there were pioneering psychologists in the 70s
that went past the work of Stan Groth, that said
that, like, they didn't deal with the concept of
spiritual emergency like he did. Speaker 1 They
were saying that psychosis itself, acute
psychosis is an intended reorganization of the
psyche. That's what's really going on. And this
and so if you could support that reorganization
without meds and just a lot of patients, they
can come through. And there were places like,
a clinic called Sutaria House where they would
just practice being with people as opposed to
doing something to them. Speaker 1 And they
were reporting an 85% recovery rate with people
in their first break. Okay. And that was very
important. So yeah, they were sending people
home just after a week stay of, you know, taking
care of them and being very supportive. And that
was like a huge eye opener. You know, that was a
huge eye opener. And that got me really like, oh,
well, I think I can do this. Speaker 1 You know,
I think I can do this. Speaker 2 Yes, yes. So,
so you found in that situation you were able
to bring, you know, knowledge and wisdom and,
a perspective to, to your niece that nobody else
in that environment seemed to be bringing. Like,
like did it seem that the doctors that were, you
know, they're there to help her, but if they're
not trained in it or they don't know any of this
stuff, or they think it's all kind of woowoo,
spiritual, weird stuff that has nothing to do with
this, you know, biology or, you know, the chemical
imbalance, that whole that whole thing, that whole
story that keeps getting repeated. Speaker 2 Wow.
Yeah, yeah. How incredible. So how were people
receptive to you when you were bringing this
stuff stuff up? Were people letting you, like,
explain these things, or did you feel you had to,
you know, your mouth closed in doctor's offices
or what? Speaker 1 It was a bit of a battle. And,
what happened was after doing four months of
research into these pioneering psychologists,
I was going to go back to the family and say,
look, she, let's take her off the medications.
If she goes back into psychosis, will support
or through it like I'm learning about. You can
do this with this Satara house method of being
versus doing. Speaker 1 And just as I was ready
to go back to the family, her sister came back
from Europe and went into psychosis. My like,
yeah, it's unbelievable. Four months apart, two
sisters with no psychiatric history went into
non-owner states. It's unbelievable. Yeah. And
she knew what happened to her younger sister. So
I call them Ana. They're fake names. But Ana, the
younger sister, Eliana, the older sister, Ileana,
came to us first and we supported her. Speaker
1 We didn't even tell her parents we had her.
And we supported her, right through her first
psychosis. Took her back to the family. She was
still ungrounded, but she wasn't kind of crazy.
Okay. And then she had a second episode that we
couldn't help her with, and she was medicated, but
then she. She only agreed to go out, stay on the
meds for two weeks. Speaker 1 When she went off
the meds, she went into psychosis again, and we
had agreed with the family that we would support
her for that third time. And we did. And it didn't
take long. And then she was able to go back to
university. Medication free, completely grounded,
finish the year with honors, you know, went off
to an amazing job and worked in 11 different
countries. Speaker 1 And eventually her master's
degree, now seven years in the future, it would
start to come up again. Okay. So it start to
come up again. But we got her through, we got her
through university, and she had those seven years
medication free. And because we got her grounded
and we knew we got her grounded right away in the
beginning, then it was like, well, this is my life
mission. Speaker 1 This is what I have to do here.
And this thing, this thing that I thought was a 1
in 20,000 kind of experience, like what I had all
of a sudden I was realizing it was more like 1 in
20, because bipolar disorder apparently affects
5% of people. So I was like, wow, this is a one
and 20. Speaker 1 This isn't a 1 in 20,000. And
that got me going. Oh, put it that way. You know,
and that's really the whole story of the first
book, you know. Spoiler alert. Speaker 2 Yeah,
yeah. Wow. No, no, it sounds fascinating. And,
definitely, again, you have the PDF. I, we linked
it below. Yeah. So even just hearing about your 80
pages worth in the landmark form, I'm curious to,
to read more about that. So, Wow, that's so
incredible. I mean, what what a you know,
I think we could bridge this into, like, the talk
of synchronicities and coincidences in general.
Speaker 2 Where do you. Because it sounds like the
in this there's, you know, those are synchronistic
things. Those are coincidences to me. Oh, yeah.
Strange way. Like, how do you where do you. This
is an impossible question. I know, but where do
where do you kind of draw the edge? Where's the
sanity when it comes to synchronicity and
coincidences? Speaker 2 Because, you know,
when I was in the. Speaker 1 And it's.
Speaker 2 Impossible question. Right. But,
I still these days, I feel very sane and grounded
in my spirituality in these sorts of experiences.
But I still have times where, you know, there's
a couple weeks, couple months where I have these
synchronistic, coincidental instances,
but compared them to my synchronistic,
coincidental instances back, you know, when I was
a bit more ungrounded, they were very, if I try
to explain them to someone in a logical manner, I
just kind of sounded off the wall like it really
would not make any sense. Speaker 2 Whereas now I
think I could be able to explain those things and
they feel personal to me, and I could articulate
them to someone elsewhere. You know, it's like,
hey, this is part of my spiritual experience. But
anyway, yeah. So I guess where do we draw the edge
of of sanity and synchronistic coincidences?
Speaker 1 It's tricky. It's tricky. You know,
I told the family, I said one of the things I
had to struggle with when I came back from the
hospital was, you know, is this real or am I
dreaming? And they said, when did you figure
it out? And I said, I never did. I just got used
to it. Speaker 1 And what I meant was, it's like
we think we're in some sort of a firm or fixed
reality here with logical reasoning and stuff
like that. But then every once in a while we have
kind of dreamlike material kick in, which is which
is what you're talking about. So synchronicity, I
mean, when that happens, there are times when it's
actually impossible. Speaker 1 What just happened?
You know, I tell a story in my second book where
I had a dream, and it's a long story, but part of
it is I had a dream in like, I think it was about
2016 August 2016 about seeing myself falling at
a distance. I was watching myself falling into
a jungle canopy, and I was wondering if I had.
Speaker 1 Actually, when I woke up, I wondered
if I had entered into a new parallel universe of
some kind, like had my reality really shifted. In
a way, the eight months in the future. So March
of 2017, I go with a client, we're in Mexico and
we go see King Kong Skull Island together. It
was like a little break from our retreat work,
and the opening scene is the silhouette of a man
falling into a jungle canopy with the sun behind
him. Speaker 1 Wow. So I had seen the entrance to
that movie eight months earlier, and I was telling
the client's mother the story of that dream just
before we went into the movie theater. Whoa. Yeah.
And she popped up and said, song your dream? And
I said, yeah, yeah, yeah, I don't know what to do
with this. Yeah. What do I do with this? Speaker
1 This is just this is too much, you know? So,
I think life has a dreamlike quality like that.
And also our dreams have a kind of a reality
quality. Like they impact us more than we think
we do. Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. I mean, you mentioned
shamans, you know, back in the day of shamans, and
it was a very important, I'm sure if we if they
projected into the future and they learned that we
kind of just ignore those eight hours where we go
to a different plane of reality every night. It's
not really a thing in our culture. Speaker 2 It's
like I had this crazy dream. It was crazy. Anyway,
what are you having for breakfast this morning?
You know, it's, it's. I think back in the day,
I think there was, you know, sets of humans that
used the dream world maybe just as much as the
regular world. Speaker 1 The the difference for
them, though, what I've learned, because I've
studied a lot of this stuff, is they really
looked at the dream world as another reality,
like this one, you know? So, for example, if
you if you dream that your best friend is having
sex with your girlfriend, it happened and you're
going to go talk to your friend about it, like,
you know, it's serious. Speaker 1 Yeah, yeah,
but but the level of importance is kind of equal.
You know, the interpretations are different. But
the for me, my dream world is very important. And
it's part of the therapeutic work I do, you know.
Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah, absolutely. Okay. So I'm
trying to think of so say the listener right now,
this is probably all super interesting to someone
who's in this boat, but say that maybe they've
been diagnosed with bipolar, and they, they feel
okay. Maybe they're, they're medicated or maybe,
maybe they're not even diagnosed. Maybe they're
experiencing some things right now that,
might be up that alley or somebody says they
have bipolar or their, their sister has bipolar,
and so they think it's genetic, etc., etc..
Speaker 2 And they're listening to this stuff and
they're like, what the what does this have to do
with spirituality? I guess like. Speaker 1 Well,
I think in the bigger picture, yeah. Spiritual
experiences like the one I had or even things
like psychedelic experiences, for example, people
often report having spiritual experiences while
on taking LSD and things like that, or peak
experience that can happen even during sports.
Or different kinds of rituals. They, they give
you a taste of this other dimension. Speaker 1 But
what you're doing with it is, is kind of
the important thing. And, and I think that,
the spiritual dimension is just leading us towards
an authenticity. You know, like I said earlier,
it's not about being normal. It's being natural,
you know? And so, when people are healing,
which is the focus of, you know, my work now,
it's about becoming more open, spontaneous,
and peaceful, you know, and present those kind
of things. Speaker 1 It's not about being this
Tony Robbins kind of super. God, you know, I
was so productive last week, I. I slayed the
world. It's like, congratulations, Mr. Ego boost.
I mean, you know, it's not about that. It's about.
It's about being really authentic and honest with
yourself. And and I think to a certain extent,
healing is about kind of cleaning out the lies,
cleaning out the bullshit we tell ourselves,
not just about other people or the lies we tell
others, but the lies we tell ourselves, parts of
us that are just not being honest with ourselves.
Speaker 1 Speaker 2 I want to, I want to expand
into that more so because that that resonates with
my experience. I had a lot of things I was being
dishonest with others about and things I was being
dishonest with myself more importantly about. And
I found that. Yeah, that was, after a while, you
start when you're dishonest, you have these layers
that you begin to create almost accidentally,
of, like, these lies that you have to keep up
with. Speaker 2 Again, whether it's socially or
just inwardly, and then you kind of lose yourself
in between. Is that is that something that you
would say is fairly common with, with people
who have these experiences? Is there some sort of
external or internal lie that maybe even they're
not even aware of? Maybe there's some childhood
thing that happened that they're not really fully
able to be truthful with in the moment? Speaker
2 Is this common? Speaker 1 Right. Well, like
the root of the disorder is trauma, okay. That's
a big deal. And trauma in itself is kind of a lie
because it's taking a part of an experience that
was so painful that we deny the emotion itself
like a, you know, we just don't don't accept that
that happened. And the best example, I think,
is when you see someone who is at the funeral of
a loved one and they don't cry, and then they'll
even ask themselves later, they'll say, I don't
understand why I didn't cry. Speaker 1 You know,
I loved him. You know, when people go to therapy,
why didn't I cry at my father's funeral? You know?
And the reason is they're just so devastated that
their psyche has just checked it out and said,
no, we're not going there. And then and then it
becomes locked into this energetic system and
can be a trauma that leads to a deeper disorder.
Speaker 1 And so how does our. Speaker 2 He, have
you heard of a read the book The Body Keeps the
score. You've heard of that one? Speaker 1 I,
I haven't read it. I should treat it.
Really? Speaker 2 It's always brought up,
right? Yeah. It's always worth. Speaker 1 Yeah,
it's always brought up. I just feel like I it's
like I know. Speaker 2 Yeah. You're going to
be nodding your head during the entire book.
Yeah. Yeah. Speaker 1 Well, I yeah, it's a huge
book though. Very influential. Yeah. Speaker 2 I
mean, I think I would just the book seems to be
my doorway to the conversation about kind of,
I think of, like our fascia, our myofascial
system. I think it's kind of like a lot of our
spiritual like postures with, with the world.
Speaker 1 Okay. Speaker 2 I, I kind of wonder,
so, like, how is it how do you see trauma being
stored or is it stored in our physical body? Is
it held? Speaker 1 Yeah. I see it in I see it
semantically, like it's in our bioenergetics
system. You could call it a chakra system or
kundalini system. And incidentally, a year
after my hospitalization, I went for Rolfing,
which breaks up the fascia tissue, you know,
and when you do that, sometimes that does release
emotions. And I did have some of that happen in
particular. Speaker 1 Okay. Yeah. It's a very have
you heard of Rolfing? It's a very intense. It's a
very intense massage where the focus is on, kind
of breaking up the fascia tissue, which in the
fascia tissue is like, what connects your bones
together, I think. And once that's broken up,
you just feel a lot more fluid and expansive.
Speaker 1 But it's been known that people will
cry on the massage table from having this Rolfing
technique done to them, you know? So for me,
the trauma is carried throughout the body,
particularly along the chocolate line. But it
can be in other, other parts. And so the key
to healing is to, work on that. The therapy
should be somatic, it should be working with
the body. Speaker 1 And so in my second book,
I talk about the private retreats that I set up.
Took me a long time to figure it out, but by 2013,
I started doing private retreats for people. And
in those retreats, I was using a technique from
Stan Grof, derivation of the technique of Hall of
Tropic Breathwork. And with the Tropic Breathwork,
you're over breathing in a very safe space in your
in a mat and yoga pants, and there's some powerful
music playing and you were you're with a trained
facilitator. Speaker 1 Certified facilitator. You
do this over breathing. And then when you do that,
the unconscious comes up and part of it is very
physical. So there's a thing that happens called
the tani, where your whole body can lock up your
face, your neck and some people get so locked up
they can barely even talk. And they can go into
panic. Speaker 1 So it's good to remind people
that this can happen beforehand, and they can
be locked up there for like 30 minutes, and then
the whole thing just relaxes and they feel more
relaxed than they've ever had for their entire
life. So this is just like a wave of mini traumas
through the whole body that just being released.
You know, that tension. Speaker 1 Tension.
Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. And so, so so you've you've
experienced through my fast release and then so
in, in your, in your retreats that you set up,
I know you've talked a lot about a lot about
breathwork and you, you have developed your own.
You kind of switch that into you have your own
bipolar breathing. Can you tell me about that?
Speaker 1 Yeah. That's right. Well, breathwork is
a formatted thing because there's a million ways
to do breathwork. You know, you can do breathing.
That's just like relaxation meditation. You can do
things that are supposed to active, activate your
kundalini processes, you know, pranayama
and things like that. But with breathwork,
you've got, a safe space trained facilitator,
like I said, powerful music. Speaker 1 It's a
three hour session, generally in a group. Okay,
it can be private, but it's also in a group. And
that's the format. And that was contraindicated
for people with deeper disorders because they were
afraid that it might open up too much. And the
group setting or the limited time frame would be
a wouldn't be a safe enough container for someone
who's dealing with more difficult issues like you
might have if you've got bipolar schizophrenia.
Speaker 1 So I said to myself, well,
I'm not doing anything right now. How about if I
start my own retreat? And that way I give people
unlimited time frame and unlimited attention,
just private attention. And and I insist that
they bring a volunteer, a volunteer supporter, so
that I'm I'm not on my own. I can get breaks while
they can still be supervised. Speaker 1 The family
knows somebody is with them, so they know I'm not
just some weirdo from the internet. Somebody
from the family is sort of involved. Yeah.
And then with the Bipolar Breathwork, I just made
a few adjustments, which is they can start and
stop whenever they want, you know? So if they just
decide after 20 minutes, that's it. Speaker 1 I
say, okay, that's it. And we stop and then we come
back to it when they want. That's the first thing.
And then there's the undivided attention. And I
can also customize the music depending on where
they're at. So they were the three of the big
adjustments I made early on, you know, and the
results were incredible. Speaker 2 Yeah. So what
are the kind of experiences people that you saw
people having? Speaker 1 Yeah. Well, to, to point
out, like the somatic aspect to this whole thing,
you know, which is, the kundalini and the blocked
energy. My first client had been hospitalized, I
think, about ten times and, every year for about a
month, for six years. And when I went to work with
her, she had a pain in her coccyx that was so bad
she couldn't sit down for more than ten minutes,
and she couldn't lay on her back in bed. Speaker
1 All right. And in the fifth breathwork session
we did. She didn't move a muscle. Very quiet.
I thought nothing was happening. And then she
came back and she told me hot energy came shooting
out of her coccyx, up the spine, into the shoulder
blades, down through the hands and the pain
that she had been to. Six medical doctors for,
and they had no answer for her. Speaker 1 The pain
was gone, you know, after five sessions we knew
right away and synchronistic. We knew it was part
of the disorder. I had suspected it. She had told
me about the coccyx pain even before I went there.
And, when that cleared up, well, that cleared up.
I thought she had been healed. Okay. Why not? I'm
a genius. Speaker 1 This is done. Here's my bill.
I'm Jesus now. Yeah. I'm Jesus, and I'm Jesus. But
she did have an episode a couple of months later,
and I got on the phone with her. I said, I'm
coming back to Romania. I live in Brazil and come
back to Romania, and you don't need to pay for
anything. And we did a second retreat the second
year, 2014, and then she was meds free for five
years. Speaker 1 She was. That's for five years
after that. So again, it was like she come in
2016, I met her again. I was in Romania three
years in a row. Synchronistic. And she came back,
she visited me and she said, Sean, I've been off
my meds for you. That hasn't happened since I was
20 years old, you know, like for 15 years, you
know, and she was able to remain off her meds for
five years, you know? Speaker 1 Yeah. So, you know
that she was my first client, and then after that,
my next two clients in Germany and Finland had
incredible success. And they're both completely
out of the psychiatric system. They had no
medications, no relapses for over a decade now.
Yeah, that that's incredible. Speaker 2 Okay,
so bring me bring in someone who I think you you
and I. It's not that shocking. To hear, you know,
there's this physical pain in someone's body. It's
it's at this area where we know it's like, okay,
this is like, maybe stuck energy in your root
chakra. That'd be language that you and I would
probably know, but someone else would be like,
wait, okay, so you're saying this lady went in
to six different doctors? Speaker 2 She had pain
that couldn't get solved. It was not on an x ray
anywhere. And she breathed in. It helped, you
know. Speaker 1 Yeah, yeah. And then try to tell
a psychiatrist that, you know, the roots of her
mental illness are spiritual and in her ass. Yeah,
yeah. It's like, okay, I give up. I can't do
that. Right? Speaker 2 Yeah, yeah. But clearly
you've had success with it. So. So how do you, how
do you break this down to people. How do you how
do you explain this in a way that, that people can
wrap their heads around? Speaker 1 I made a lot of
YouTube videos, show a lot of YouTube videos, and
I and I, and I made, well, and the books help. But
what I learn on YouTube is that even though I'm
talking about information that is pretty complex,
you can take the ideas as long as you break them
down into small pieces and give people things that
they can relate to. Speaker 1 Like one of my most
popular videos that people still watch was like,
what about the spiritual delusions?
And I called it, I think I called it,
is it bipolar disorder or spiritual enlightenment?
And then I talk about the delusions that look like
enlightenment. And I think I say, so whether
you're a Buddhist monk going through this,
in a cave in in Tibet or you're a teenager
in Chicago who just took some LSD, your
experience look pretty much the same. Speaker 1
You know, there's not and funny enough, intensive
meditation that going on a ten day retreat is a
very common trigger for acute psychosis that gets
people labeled bipolar, and then they're medicated
for life, you know, so it's not just all these
kids are taking drugs and and now they've ruined
their lives and they're on these meds. It's very
common drug use. Speaker 1 But on the other end,
intensive medication meditation can bring the
same thing. Yeah. Yeah. Speaker 2 Well, you had,
didn't you have a ten day Vipassana experience?
Didn't you have a spiritual experience on
it? Speaker 1 Yeah, I had my chair. I had 1
in 2. The 2009. And energetically it felt stronger
than what put me in the psychiatric hospital over.
And it left, like, again, explosion at the heart
chakra, all my organs shaking, vibrating, crying,
but more tears of joy. But I was so shook up.
And this is during the meditation that I was
afraid to walk back to my room because there was
a hillside trail, and I thought that if I fainted,
I might fall down the hill and never be seen
again, you know, this kind of thing. Speaker 1 So
and I was basically in bed every morning for the
next five days, and it was stronger in a Kundalini
sense than what put me in the hospital. But I by
that point, I knew what I was doing. I had been
around the work. I had been my mission for three
years. So when this Kundalini process unfolded,
then it was I was a bit more ready for the whole
thing, you know, and then and then the heart of
the Kundalini stuff continued. Speaker 1 For the
next six months, I'd be in bed with my wife and
then, you know, goodnight. Oh, like, oh, what's
that? Just hot pins in my toes. Thank you. Yeah,
yeah. Just a Korea, honey. Don't worry.
Yeah. Is that what they are? Korea's. Oh,
the Korea's the prayer. Right. Speaker 2 Well so
Korea my understanding is Korea is the involuntary
movement. It is the, like the sudden, like the,
you know, you're trying to you're in meditation
and you can't really help but, you know, anybody
who's going through a Kundalini experience,
especially for doing a lot of yoga, too, you
can't really help but like, do all that kind
of stuff. Speaker 2 That's my understanding of
Korea. I could be a little bit wrong on that,
but. Speaker 1 Okay. Yeah, yeah. No. And and I
still work with Kundalini processes to this day,
go through a lot of jerking. But, but for the
first six months, it was quite uncomfortable.
Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. Okay. Well, so where do you
where would you say that? You sit with it now,
after, you know, after this many years of of it
as your personal experience where, you know, like,
like when someone comes in and then they would
like to know kind of your, your background of
not only your experience with Kundalini and your
spirituality and everything. Speaker 2 What is
kind of your explanation to them? Like, hey, I had
this experience happen. Here's how I see it now.
Because because to me, you come across as very
grounded with this sort of thing. And so I kind
of wonder, how you observe yourself or how
you see others seeing you when you explain
it? Speaker 1 Well, I don't talk about it that
much for regular people. I am not the kind of
person like I look for the open door, or I look
for people who seem to be looking for this kind
of help. And then if they come to me like. Like I
say, you guy like you, you know, you're very open,
you're very receptive and you're curious. Speaker
1 You want to know, right? But I don't stand on
the street corner trying to tell everybody about
what happened to me. And when people say, oh,
how do I convince my family to understand that
what I went through spiritual, I tell them,
I say, don't just, look for someone who's open,
or if someone comes to you and you put a few
feelers out there and they're opening curious.
Speaker 1 Sure. Talk about it. But if not,
just just keep it to yourself because people
get threatened by this kind of thing. And and
if it's you feel like they're not listening in
the beginning, they're not you're not going to
change their mind. You're not going to change
their mind. Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. I agree,
I where I've come at with my experience with it
is yeah, I'm in that same boat, like, I don't,
I don't go advertising it. Sometimes it's like I
why I'll go many months without even talking about
it with friends or whatever. It's like it's crazy.
It's like very profound. You know, to me, very
important experience happened to me that changed
the course of my life. Speaker 2 But it's like,
I mean, really thought about it much, whatever.
But, I'll note that, it will come up in cool
conversations where it feels natural, it feels
safe. It feels that I can be useful to the person
that I'm talking to. I actually had one time on
a plane. I'm mostly an introvert in public on
planes. Speaker 2 You know, I'm kind of just like
to, you know, have my hood up, have headphones on,
just kind of keep to myself. I don't typically
dive into a bunch of deep conversations on planes,
but, I had one pay a year and a half, two
years ago where, I started talking to this,
to this girl next to me. Speaker 2 She was super,
super cool, super fly. And over the course of
the time was like a five hour flight. I ended up
learning that her sister had been going through,
basically psychosis. And she was like, going
through all these things. And I allowed this
girl to tell me quite a bit before I even was
like. Speaker 1 Whoa, here's. Speaker 2 Kind of
my thoughts if you're willing to hear, you know,
and I kind of trying to explain without, you know,
this girl I'd never heard, you know, these terms
Kundalini or, you know, she doesn't use terms like
chakra. I think she had like more of a Christian
background. So, you know, some of those terms
in itself are sometimes people can think they're
demonic for some reason. Speaker 2 But but anyway,
so I ended up a great connection. I gave
her a lot of these resources. I was like,
hey, check out this channel, check out this
person. This could be all totally, you know,
just my perception, you know? But maybe send your
sister these, see what she thinks, maybe have a
conversation with her. Maybe you could talk to
your mother about these things. Speaker 2 You
know, just to open up the conversation with your
sister. And she seemed to be very, very grateful.
And I was like, you know, that was cool that I
was able to this stuff that I'm obsessed with,
this stuff that I like learning about, that
happened to me. I'm able to kind of casually
open up and potentially maybe I helped out that
person sister in some way. Speaker 2 I've giving
her some resources. So yeah, like I wasn't going
about looking for like, who wants to hear about my
Kundalini awakening on this plane? You know, but,
but it just happened. Speaker 1 So and I will add,
though, that, over the last 18 years of doing
this work, you know, starting in 2007, I was 20,
24 and I was making videos and writing books and
I'm doing retreats. There was often a tremendous
sense of mission and that I hadn't finished
my mission, you know, and sometimes it would
just bring me to tears, the frustration of
but just not getting where I needed to go,
you know? Speaker 1 But then when I finished the
second book here and, you know, Bipolar Awakenings
The Quest to Heal Bipolar Disorder at the end of
the book, I was just like, I've done my part. It's
like if the world just wants to just forget
about me at this point, I've done everything
I'm supposed to do. And, and I there's a sense
of relief to a certain degree. Speaker 1 And
then I created an online course, and then the
relief got deeper. And so now it's like, well,
I'm not really sure what I'm supposed to do, but I
like to talk about it. So I've started to do more
podcasts and the curiosity is kind of over. I'm
not in the research and development part of the
work. I'm I feel like I want to be just talking
about the work instead of doing it at this point,
like being a teacher instead of a therapist,
you know? Speaker 1 Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. Well,
I think it's a good spot to be, man, I, I more
and more people with the internet especially know
YouTube is such a cool thing, especially with,
you know, we live in this. It's not necessarily
a social media algorithm. It's like a, interest
algorithm at this point, you know, so somebody
starts watching, you know, they watch this one.
Speaker 2 We talk about Kundalini a lot. And,
you know, now their algorithm is going to feed
on more, more Kundalini type stuff, which I do
I do think this could be another interesting part
of our conversation, Sean, is do you think that,
like philosophizing and reading about this
content can cause a Kundalini awakening,
do you think content for sure. Speaker 1 Yeah.
My videos, well, my videos have caused psychosis
for people. Just watching my videos is just
like Kundalini awakening. You want to call
it a Kundalini awakening? I want to call
it psychosis. I my website, like my book,
it's called Bipolar Awakenings. So I kind of put
in that the paradox that this thing can cut both
ways, you know, it can be a blessing. Speaker
1 It could get leave you medicated for life,
depending on how you deal with it. Yeah. You know,
so any information about this, reading a book,
reading a spiritual text is a common what I call a
trigger. No. Common triggers are like death in the
family. Going to university is a common trigger
because you're changing is the most common trigger
because you're changing cities. Speaker 1 You're
leaving your family behind. You're being exposed
to people. You've never been exposed to people
from different parts of the country. For example,
you're typically not doing as well at
universities. You didn't you, as you
did in college, like you're probably the top
of the class in high school, then you're just
one of the dregs when you get to university can
be very challenging. Speaker 1 The ego. And you
might be doing a lot of drugs too. So you put
all that together. It's a recipe for psychosis,
you know. Yeah, yeah. Or Bipolar Awakening. It's
a recipe for bipolar awakening. We'll put it that
way. Yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 Either way, your
self will be challenged. Okay. So. So where
do you see the self? Where do you see identity? Do
you think as a culture, we should be reshaping the
way that we interpret and talk about identity in
ourselves, in these things? Speaker 1 Wow, that's
a deep question. I don't know if we're ready for
that depth, not identity. That's that's kind of
tricky. But, you see, I think we're starting to
veer there a little bit. You hear people talk. Oh,
there's one place where it really comes up a lot.
There's all of these fake videos on YouTube by,
they say they're the words of Carl Jung
and they're the words of Alan Watts,
you know? Speaker 1 But once you get past the fact
that, well, it's not really Carl Jung and it's not
really Alan Watson, they're both dead and, you
know, like, how are they? What's talking about?
Social media. He died in 1973. There was no social
media. You know, once you get past that, though,
and you and you listen to how they talk about life
and living and, this thing that's even I'm just
learning about. Speaker 1 It's still a process of
individuation, you know, where you're pulling your
projections back from the world. You know, you're
pulling back codependent relationships where
you're looking for other people to fulfill you,
you know, which is a typical marriage, you know,
that's a, a codependent relationship is a typical
marriage. But when you look at that, it's like,
okay, it's natural, but maybe it's not optimal.
Speaker 1 Maybe there's another way to sort of
come at it, you know? And I was divorced
last year and we had a very good marriage,
I think. But and we're still friends. But
there was a part of it where I realized, whoa,
hang on. Like, I've sacrificed a lot of myself
by being in this marriage. There. There's a real
codependency going on here. Speaker 1 And I got to
figure that out, you know? Yeah. So and this year
has been a lot of deep introspection and often
very painful, and a lot of somatic movement and,
jerking through the chest, the belly, the hips,
the neck, clicking anytime. I would just sort
of settle down and focus on my own emotions. It
would be like my body would take on a life of its
own. Speaker 2 Yeah. It's almost like you got to,
like, physically embody who you're now supposed to
become or something like you're, you know, like
physically changing into to who you are next or,
or something, you know. Speaker 1 And the weird
and synchronistic part would be like, I put on
one of these, like Alan Watts or or, Carl Jung
videos on YouTube and listen to them and I noticed
that sometimes my body would spontaneously jerk on
specific points. Right? Yeah. It'd be like, this
is what you're looking for, jerk. You know? And
it was like, what is doing that? Speaker 1 What
is causing my body to spontaneously convulse on
specific words in this video? Yeah. You know,
it's it's a divine. And I should bring it up
too. And and you see it in the breathwork is the
healing agent is actually a divine intelligence.
It's a higher power. You can call it God could
be aliens. It could be, could be, angels. Speaker
1 But it's definitely a higher intelligence. And
working with people on ten day retreats, you
see how it unfolds. And it's pretty amazing.
Yeah. Speaker 2 So, so how do you when you come
across someone with a more atheistic background,
who, who, who, like I said before, you know,
doesn't necessarily love all these spiritual
words, doesn't really have a place in their, you
know, psyche or understanding of who they are for
kind of, you know, this, this divine being much
larger than, you know, my, my, lowercase me self,
how do you how do you navigate that with them?
Speaker 2 Like, are they able to if you're able
to describe like nature or the laws of nature,
does that help with them to to kind of penetrate
that or. Speaker 1 No, it doesn't help. And this
is where the work of Ken Wilber really comes
in. And Ken Wilber talks about the evolution of
consciousness. Right? Yeah. And one of the things
he says is that the first stages of consciousness,
like the first six stages, and we have four that
are very common. The first two are very infantile,
generally are related to illness, and then the
next four are pretty common. Speaker 1 And they're
all trying to get the other people to see the
world the way they think. And the biggest, the
strongest example is when a religious person who
is constantly trying to convert other people to
their religion, you know, but at the same time,
the the diversity crowd, the LGBTQ crowd, they
do the same thing. I mean, if you don't see the
world through their lens, the MAGA crowd, if you
don't see the world through their lens, it's like,
you know, you're I don't know, you need to be
deported. Speaker 2 There's bad other. Yeah.
You're evil. Speaker 1 Yeah, yeah. So so they
will see different stages of consciousness,
will see the other person as evil or stupid,
or. Yeah, like a sinner or just something's
very wrong with them, you know? But at a certain,
like, once you realize the developments going on,
your intention is to help people out. And so if
somebody is, say, say, for example, you got a,
a former drug addict who goes to church
every Sunday and that's what's holding his
life together. Speaker 1 Beautiful. That's where
he's supposed to be. Is he a racist? Sure. He's
a racist. Let him be a racist. He's got bigger
issues in his racism because he's going to die
if he doesn't, if he leaves this church, you know?
But then other people are struggling with certain
stages. Like what? Maybe. Maybe you're getting
more rational and you're wondering, well, is Jesus
even real? Speaker 1 You know, if you're having
these kind of thoughts or, then you can introduce
to them ideas that are a little more atheistic,
because that would be an actual step forward,
you know, to to get people thinking rationally
is a step forward. But then what happens when
people are atheistic is eventually they lose
meaning in life? Like, what's the point of
living? Speaker 1 You know, existential angst is a
very common depression for people with atheism or.
Yeah, like it's a disease or something. And
I was one of those people I just when I was
at the early agnostic, which is like where you
scientifically believe that it's impossible to
prove that God does or doesn't exist. I felt
like I was in a lost world, man. Speaker 1 I
was just I didn't know what to do with my life
in my 20s that followed depression, you know.
But then coming out of that atheism, if somebody
is really in that existential angst, like if
they're proud to be an atheist and are successful
in they're doing well in their materialistic good,
let them go. Let him do his thing. Speaker 1 But
if he's struggling, then you could say, well,
what's your intuition telling you? You know,
do you want to stay in your job? Do you want
to live in the city? Do you want to stay in this
relationship? If the answers are no, it's like,
well, what then? What is your deeper intuition
saying? And once we tap into the intuition, then
we're starting to follow like the inner voice of
God, you know, like this, this divine intelligence
within or or in a bigger picture, even if you want
to go way out there, the quantum field, like the
quantum intelligence, you know, because I'm a
parallel universe guy at this point, you know,
so I think Speaker 1 there's a whole bunch of
Seans, you know, there's one, Sean, that the drug
addict and one Sean's a priest and there's another
Sean that's a doctor somewhere. And. And then I
don't know what the hell I'm doing here, but it's
it's pretty trippy, I can tell you that. Yeah,
yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. Another not saying he he
has a thing. He elixir piece like I, I'm in this
one over here. How did you get into that one over
there? Speaker 1 He says that it's always really
something like that. Something like that. Yeah.
Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah. But, Yeah, I like that,
though, you know, trying to find a way in their
language that doesn't, you know, close them off,
you know, because I find that, like, you know, a
lot of people shut down with a lot of these, a lot
of these words, you know, a lot of these therapy
speak and spiritual language and all of this stuff
nowadays is, it's not only a lot, but it's very,
like, like I said before, triggering, you know,
like just a few sentences can really make someone
lock up and then, you know, you're not going to
really get any progress with them. Speaker 1 Yeah.
And everybody's everybody's on their own journey.
And to a certain degree, as much as you want to
help somebody and I want to help a lot of people,
but that journey does need to be respected.
To the point where I'm just kind of I think
I'm more than kind of nonchalant about what I'm
doing now more than any other time. Speaker 1 And
then September, believe me, I wasn't in, but I
think I had some sort of a breakthrough of, of,
of a sort after an extremely painful September.
And then now it's more just like, oh, good, let's
go to the beach, you know, and just accept what's
coming. Yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 Well, happy November
to you, sir. Speaker 1 Thank you. Yeah, it's
been a better month, man. Yeah. Paradoxically,
drinking a lot of beer lately. Funny enough,
it's like, hey, I've been Mr. no drinks,
but I'm living in a town where there's just a
lot of drunks in this town. Yeah, and, I meet my
friends on the weekend, and we have some drinks,
and I do it more to be social than anything else,
but. Speaker 1 Yeah. Yeah. Speaker 2 You know,
you know, I, I thought about, two things lately,
both alcohol, the, the liquid courage, as they
call it, as well as small talk. You know, I went
through periods where I was very against both.
And, I thought it was so much cooler than small
talk. And then, Yeah. I've really been thinking
a lot lately. Speaker 2 These last few months
of how great small talk really is to just. We're
we're just we're kind of looking for a connection.
It's not so easy to just dive layers deep with a
stranger right away. You don't always want that.
It's okay to like how do I find a way to just
smile with another individual? And sometimes it's
laughing about the silly traffic or the weather,
you know? Speaker 2 And in, in that same realm,
as much as, like, alcohol, you know, it's a spirit
and, you know, it has all these negative things.
We deal with any sort of like depression or
bipolar. Maybe alcohol isn't always your friend,
but, it's also, you know, half a beer in, and
I'm remembering how much I love this friend that
I'm getting to have a conversation with and just
talking about whatever without it needing to be
all spiritual and deep. Speaker 2 We're, you know,
laughing about fart jokes or whatever it is you're
connecting, right? You know, those simple things
that at some point in your path, you push away,
they come back around. Speaker 1 Yeah. And I
think that's a little bit synchronistic in my
own process because you're saying this because
I'm a person who does not like small talk. Like,
really? But now I'm living in a city by myself.
I've got a few close friends. Well, I've got a few
friends here and I'm learning that superficial
conversation is just the way it's going to be,
and you might as well enjoy it, you know? Speaker
1 Yeah. And so I am more active about the small
talk. How's the weather? You know, this kind of
thing. What are you doing this weekend? Well,
you kind of fine man that. Speaker 2 This this is
kind of, like, a little bit corny, right? But you
kind of find that you could still find a way to
love. Love someone without, like, your favorite
language, you know, like, I can go to a if I'm
on a road trip and I'm in Louisiana and I stop
at a gas station and I can tell maybe the person
is having a rough day or whatever, maybe I don't
even analyze their life at all. Speaker 2 And I
just have a quick little two minute conversation,
and it's kind of silly about whatever they were
talking about. It has nothing. They didn't learn
about my deep knowledge of philosophy, or they
didn't learn about my, whatever thing that I
think is going to bring me joy or happiness. But
I walked away and I'm chipper as I'm walking out
of that store and they're smiling. Speaker
2 Whatever. You know, that's I don't know,
that's that's connection. Speaker 1 You know, it's
it. To tell you the truth, I think the best thing
like, because I live alone and sometimes I can
get a little lonely. Sometimes I think the best
thing I can do for my own loneliness when
it comes up, is just get it. An Uber broken
Uber for like 20 minutes. You know, I have great
conversations with Uber drivers. Speaker 1 Yeah,
yeah, they got nothing to do. They're driving
around all day and I've had some really fun,
funny conversations with Uber drivers both here
in Brazil and in Canada. Yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 I
had a guy thank me the other day, actually,
for talking to him because he was a little
bit, a little bit of a language barrier, and I
could tell he probably gets a little frustrated
trying to. But, you know, we were talking it
was a little clunky, but at the end he was like,
thank you very much for for taking the time to
talk to me. Speaker 2 I'm like, dude, of course.
Like, I can't believe you just had to thank me
for talking to you, you know? Speaker 1 But, I
remember I had an absolute nightmare of, retreat
in India. In South India. I can't go into the
details. It's in the book. But they threw me out.
They got spooked by what I was doing. Basically, I
went and they put me in this taxi for a four hour
taxi ride back to the airport. And at one point,
I just go rush. Speaker 1 Yes, sir. Do I seem like
a bad person to you? He goes, no, sir. You are a
cool guy, sir. Yeah, man. It was like Raj was my
therapist in that moment, you know? Yeah. Sorry
for the Indian accent. I had to do it. Speaker 2
No, I love it. I'm so glad you did. I'm a huge fan
of, comedy. I'm actually going to a comedy show
tonight, so I'm a bum. Oh, great. And anywhere I
could insert comedy into the conversation, I'm in,
man. So thank you for it. Speaker 1 Okay. Yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 Okay. Well, I want
to I would love to talk a little bit more about
Kundalini itself, if you don't mind. So. Speaker
1 For it. Speaker 2 I'm always, like I said,
since the beginning, I'm always kind of trying to
bring along the person who's new. Maybe they're in
the car ride or they're, you know, they're with
their significant other who likes my podcast,
and they don't really know. I like to like,
bring people aboard so they can feel like
they're part of the conversation. Speaker 2 You
know, you know as well as I do that Kundalini is,
it instantly feels very far fetched. It's like, if
this is an energetic snake coming out of my butt,
what are you talking about? You know, but,
bring it back to kind of like, this divine
energy that is, you know, within all humans.
And it could be, you know, activated release,
like, like, I think the best way to describe it,
it seems cheap to those people when I say it,
I feel. Speaker 2 But, I would say, like, you
know, Jesus had an awakened Kundalini. You know,
I would say the Buddha had an awakened Kundalini.
I don't know these for a fact, but I think it's
just a good way of explaining it. Speaker 1
Yeah. Speaker 2 They were, you know, again,
not the US having Kundalini awakening. It's means
that we're like now enlightened as just regular
people or something. But, I don't know, how do
you demystify the word Kundalini, Mr. Blackwell?
Speaker 1 I do I do demystify it. Well, I like
to start by saying that there was in like about
the 1930s, there was a guy named Gopi Krishna
in India, and he had dedicated his life to God
and meditating every day. And then all of a sudden
it started with him. And one of his symptoms was,
he just had this insatiable thirst. Speaker 1
And no matter how much he drank, his mouth was
always hot. He was always burning. That was one
of his symptoms of his kundalini process. Okay.
My first client, Livia, she was dealing with the
same thing. She called me a few months after one
of our retreats, chant. I'm just drinking water
all the time. I can't get rid of this burning
mouth. Speaker 1 You know Gopi Krishna, at the
time, he knew he was in some sort of a kundalini
process and he knew that it looked very similar to
madness. He contacted every guru. He could get in
touch with every mystic guru in India that he was
aware of, and there were a lot he couldn't find
a single one that had had a Kundalini experience.
Speaker 1 Wow. Okay, so we're talking about Indian
mystics in 1935. These experiences are very common
now for completely untrained people, okay. Regular
teenagers having Kundalini experiences, they don't
know what's going on, but sometimes they just
follow their intuition and spontaneously start
to move with this stuff to sort of unlock it,
you know, and other people become afraid of it,
you know? Speaker 1 So what to make of it? I think
that we are in a bigger kind of a global awakening
of some kind. Groff was big on the astrology of
the whole thing, and I think that. And this gets
woowoo. Okay, this does get woowoo, but I think
that there's a just a need for authenticity
that's happening now in our world that earlier
generations never thought to go to, even with
their most intimate partners. Speaker 1 You know,
like you and I are having, I think, an incredible
conversation, you know, which I have not had with,
oh, I could probably count on, you know, my
finger, my fingers, how many times I've had a
conversation where I felt someone is so just with
me and real, you know, it's for the most part,
that authentic connection. Speaker 1 I think
you're better off trying to find that with
your cat and with, you know, a family member or
something like that. So there's something there's
a demand for authenticity. And one of the things
that's coming up, I'm sort of meandering around
the question, but please. Speaker 2 Do you Grant.
Yeah. Speaker 1 Where where we met on Pod Match.
There's all kinds of pod match profiles of of a
bunch of different podcasts. And the one word that
keeps coming up in everybody's podcast profile
right now is the word roar. Everybody's saying,
oh, this is the place for roar, conversation.
Roar, roar, roar. Unfiltered, unfiltered, raw,
unfiltered, raw filter. And almost to the point
where it's kind of a joke, but people, I think
maybe it's because of the AI coming in are getting
brittle against inauthenticity. Speaker 1 They
want real life experience, they want real
connection. And to have that, you do need to get
more honest with yourself, you know? And therapy
can help. But I don't know. I think there's a lot
online that that can help these days as well. And
it's a, it's an introspective movement. And once
you start to get introspective, the Kundalini is
just going to pop, you know, eventually it's going
to it's going to show up in different ways and
you're going to realize it eventually. Speaker 1 I
think, yeah. Speaker 2 You know, wouldn't that
be wild if all the podcasters just start having
Kundalini awakenings? Speaker 1 Well, it's the
end. It's a different kind of conversation you
have as a podcaster too, because you guys are
having and I've done some podcasts too, but it's
like, okay, here we are, 60 minutes, just me and
you uninterrupted, you know? Yeah. Speaker 2 How
often you do that? Speaker 1 Not too often.
Yeah. Not too often. Yeah. Yeah. About things
you're genuinely interested in you know. So
it's a, it's a very different kind of thing. I,
I feel more connected to you, for example, than
I would, my, neighbor that I see every day,
that I see physically every day. Yeah. You
know, I've never had a conversation like this
with him. Speaker 1 You know, we talk about the
women at the beach, we talk about the drunks,
we talk about some gossip about the neighbors.
And. And that's our thing, right? Yeah.
Yeah. Speaker 2 We're like, what's around us right
here, you know? Yeah. You know, you don't get too
ethereal or too meta or too birds eye systems
thinking. Speaker 1 You know, and we I have fun
with this guy. He's a great guy. Yeah. Of course.
But it's not. It's not like this. This is a whole
other. This is a kind of a conversation that I
think can inspire people. Yeah. Speaker 2 Yeah,
I think so, too. I mean, you know that. That's
why I like to do them. You know, obviously I love
them too. But, you know, I like to think that
there's I keep referencing, like, the listener,
you know, when I first started, that made me
starting this podcast years back was kind of at,
not like the height of it kept kind of on like the
decline of my kind of awakening. Speaker 2 And,
I was I had been listening. I was I started
basically, I want to solve all my childhood
trauma. I wanted to fix everything that was broken
about me, you know? And so I just went to town
with excavators and shovels and everything about
my psyche. And my insides, and I really just tore
it up. And I was really, you know, pretty loosey
goosey for a little while. Speaker 2 And, I was
listening to podcasts, and I was just learning so
much. And I listen to audiobooks and I'm taking
notes, and I'm just unraveling, learning so much.
And it was so fun and so great and so awesome was
just I felt like a new person every day. I'm just
shedding layers, right. And, I would hear things
on a podcast like, so, you know, a couple dorky
comedians talking about whatever. Speaker 2 In two
hours and 13 minutes in this, one guest would
say this one sentence that would just like,
I have to pause it and I have to, like, sit down.
And it just changed me. And it I'm just I've never
heard anybody talk like that, especially like
a man in this instance or whatever. And so I
would notice how just casually listening
to podcasts would profoundly change me,
you know. Speaker 2 And so that led that was a lot
of the reason why I started doing the podcast and
things too. So I, you know, I'm sure I'm not the
only person in that boat, you know? And so isn't
that cool to think that we're all changing one
another by sharing our, our personal conversations
and other people can listen in on? Speaker 1
Yeah, I've never thought about that before,
but certainly people listening to authentic,
raw conversation is going to have implications
for a real life, you know, because people will
start to be more authentic in their daily lives
with their friends and things like that. They're
going to want to open up. They're going to want to
reveal themselves more. And it's self-revelation.
Speaker 1 And as you peel back those layers,
then all of a sudden you get the tweaks and the
burning and the the heart palpitations and the
leg twitches and all that kind of goofy stuff, the
pins and the toes and yeah, yeah, those kundalini
symptoms. Speaker 2 All the fun, exciting stuff.
Okay, well, I want to be respectful of your time,
Sean, we are, getting towards the end here. So
say someone is interested in this. They love
all that you've said. You know, they're going
to go check out your websites and everything.
What's what's not only new on the horizon
for you. Speaker 2 Bipolar awakenings is
your most recent book there. Firstly, would
you this is probably a hard question to ask
an author. Would you recommend your first one
or your second book if you had to choose one
as like their first intro to your work? Speaker
1 Oh good question. If you don't know me, then,
the first one, it's an easy read. It's a two
day read, right? Nice. Yeah. The second book,
after every chapter, you need to sit down. Yeah.
You just need to be like, did this really happen?
Oh my God. And you just need to go and digest and
take a break and and it's and it's annoyingly deep
and detailed. Speaker 1 And I love it. It's for my
money is better than the Bible, but that's just my
own unbiased opinion. Speaker 2 You know, sign me
up. Sounds good. That's awesome. Speaker 1 Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 Well, cool. Okay, so so
they'll check out your newest book or maybe
dive into your older, older teachings. Speaker 1
Well, both are free PDFs on my website, Bipolar
awakenings.com, and they're. Speaker 2 Both free
PDFs. That's amazing. That's cool. Speaker 1 They
offer that. Yeah. And I and I've got some online
therapeutic approaches that I use to we haven't
had time to get into it. But you know that's
something we have. But I also do a free 30
minute consultation for people. Speaker 2 Can I
I don't want to I don't want to rush past it. We
do have a few minutes. Can you tell me a little
bit more about your online online courses? What
do you offer? What can they get into? Speaker 1
Well, on my retreats, I learned that I was picking
up the unconscious materials of my client. Like
their pain. Oh, that's. Speaker 2 I actually had
notes about this. I did want to ask about this,
so. Yes. Speaker 1 Okay. Well, I and so, to make
a real long story short, with the help of, one of
my clients who became a supporter, Monica Kettler,
I always have to give her credit, too. We realized
that we were picking up unconscious material
from the clients and that having us breathe on
behalf of the client, actually going into the
client's pain really strengthened the retreat
process. Speaker 1 Yeah. Because, for example,
I've got tons of experience in breathwork and it's
not my pain. So if I'm breathing on your behalf,
I can go into things that you're not ready for,
you know, that became standard part of our retreat
process. First my client would breathe and then
I would breathe after that. Then I learned, guess
what? Speaker 1 This works at a distance. I can do
distance work like this. And that's a long story
I get into in the book. But, so I have a thing
called distance surrogate breathwork that I can do
on people's behalf. And basically it's a two hour
session where I'm listening to breathwork music
and twitching and working, you know, working out
whatever I feel is going on. Speaker 1 And then
the client will have some sort of synchronistic
material so that they know that I'm working on
them. Most of the time it's dreams that come
afterwards where they know it's their material,
you know, they just know that this is about their
life. Like last week, I had a dream about having
to apologize for my criminally oriented brother.
Speaker 1 And this guy had a had a brother who
had been to jail, you know, I that kind of thing.
It could also be visual things that pop up during
the session, although that's less common these
days, and sometimes physical sensations and and
sometimes simultaneous physical sensations. So I
was in a session with a guy from New York, and at
about the 20 minute mark, my arms just snapped
right out of their sides. Speaker 1 And when I
finished the session, I got a text from him and
my arms just snapped right out of my sides. Whoa.
Yeah, like crazy stuff happens where it's like,
you know, you're connected, you know? So. And if
you don't, I'm open to return people's feet. So
that's something that I do for people. And I also
have a training program where I'm if people have
a supporter, I'm open to teach the right people
how to do breathwork in their own home. Speaker 1
If they've got someone who's willing to learn the
training with them. So far, I've had no takers,
but that's there too. Speaker 2 Yeah, yeah, yeah,
I guess we'll see. Speaker 1 Yeah, I keep trying
to make the work cheaper and more accessible, but
keeping it safe as well, you know. Speaker 2 Sure.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. So I, I'm sorry I keep having
more questions. Come. How do you. Monica. Speaker
2 How did you how do you. I don't want to say
protect yourself, because that sounds like, How
do you not only stay sane and protect yourself?
I guess, but, how do you, like, once you notice?
Okay, this is not only this. This is not my energy
to work with. Now, let me transmute it. But how do
you even get to the point where you can decipher
your intuitive, like, the things you're working
on versus other people's energy? Speaker 1 How
do you, Well, the first thing is that that
while it's with me, it feels like it's my own,
you know? And so I just treat it like it's my own
and go through it as if it's my own material. But
then once I look at the content and I look at how
I see, feel later, it's pretty clear that it's
the client's material. Speaker 1 Because when it's
your material and you work through it like this is
your own unconscious material surfacing, when that
happens, it leaves a lasting impression with you,
and sometimes you need to sleep on things.
You need to think about it. For example,
if you had some anger come up, you might feel
angry after the session, for example. That kind
of thing. Speaker 1 But when it's somebody else's
material, it just passes through. You like energy,
even if it's angry or shameful or a birth related,
and you just look at it, you go, it's like you're
watching the whole thing happening. It's moving
through you, and you don't have any ego in the
game. That's another part of it. It's being
done by the quantum field. Speaker 1 This,
the inner healer, is actually a healing field
that is sending that energy to you to process.
Right? So you're just acting like a servant or
something. You're just or you're just cleaning
whatever's coming your way. That's it. So, if you
think on the Big guru and I'm going to heal you,
that's not going to happen because there's too
much ego in the picture. Speaker 1 You need to
genuinely want to do this for people and, want
their best, best needs at heart, you know, and you
just filter it through like it's your own stuff.
Speaker 2 Yeah, I love that a little bit easy
actually. Speaker 1 Yeah, I. Speaker 2 Was I love
that I, I was able to ask that because I had a lot
of struggles. I think, you know, probably a lot of
people who go through this stuff or would consider
themselves somewhat of empathic, you know, in
some ways that sensitive at the very least.
And I went through a lot of struggles of absorbing
other people's energy, and it was very confusing
to me for a while. Speaker 2 It took me a while
to kind of like feel when I'm grounded in my
own body and feel when, you know, I'd be at times
where I could have, like just walking by someone,
I would suddenly be like distressed and whatever.
And instead of launching off into my solving
intellectual mind of like, why is my life this
like this and what am I doing and blah blah,
just kind of allow it. Speaker 2 And then within a
few seconds it's like passes through and I go, oh,
I don't even have to solve that. That wasn't mine
to solve. I just just passed through. Which is so
strange. Right? But, I think it's a useful thing
to learn how to do. Speaker 1 Sure. And. Yeah.
And things have happened to me on the street,
like just by accident, walking by somebody.
And then all of a sudden, I have a feeling for
a situation and all the whoa, whoa, like, yeah,
I've kind of got to be open and compassionate,
but it's generally quite spontaneous. You know,
it's not like I'm walking around, you know, in
white robes or anything like that. Speaker 2 It's
just give me your back. Yeah. Speaker 1 Yeah,
yeah. You know, congratulations. You've got
bipolar disorder, you know. Yeah. Now it's
it's just happens. I just deal with it. And,
and that's it, you know, it's it's and it's
common. I, there have been supporters who've
come on my retreats. They just really care about
the person. You know, we had a we had a girl on
one retreat, 23 years old, no experience with
my kind of psychology. Speaker 1 And then she
was falling asleep during her boyfriend session at
10:00 in the morning. Normally, when I'm absorbing
energy from a client, I'm getting really drowsy.
Really? It's like it's a magnet that sucks you in,
right? It was happening to her. So I said to her,
do you want to breathe? Afterwards the session was
over. She says, yeah. Speaker 1 She starts to go
into her boyfriend's birth process. Next thing you
know, she's like, I have to simulate a uterus for
her. And she's got her head going through my arms
and then like, I'm hanging on to her and she's
struggling out of my grip and I've got to hang
on down through the hips and the legs and the
feet like she's being born. Speaker 1 And then
I said to her, I said, did you have any sense that
that was something related to your life? And she
was like, no, that was fine. What? She just what
a trip. Yeah, yeah. And it was her boyfriend's
birth material. Speaker 2 Yeah. I mean, talking
about codependency. Speaker 1 Yeah. She had no
training at all. None. You know, so I was like,
wow, she can do the surrogate work. Then anybody
can do it for anybody if they've got the empathy.
And she did. She had. Speaker 2 Yeah. Yeah I mean
wow how incredible is that? I mean I think like
you already stated, I think a lot of us have
discovered since, especially since 2020, how we
are able to do those sorts of things virtually to,
you know, we're able to not only through
video zoom calls, but like you said,
if if you and the other person are both aware that
the hey, this is what we're going through at the
same moment together, it really does. Speaker 2 I
mean, wow, what a we have so much to learn about
the the capacity and capability of of the, the
human mind and how it integrates with physical
reality. Right? Speaker 1 Yeah. I had a call once
with a girl where I was explaining how the psychic
material comes, and I said, suppose, for example,
I'm working with you and I see a red violin,
and then I that might be something related
to your life. And then actually I said,
actually did do you play violin? And she's like,
yeah, I play violin. Speaker 1 I grew up playing
the violin. This is my favorite instrument. I was
like, oh, okay, that makes sense. Okay. You know,
these kinds of things. Yeah. So yeah. Speaker 2
Yeah, they're like little, little crumbs from,
from the, from our greater selves or crumbs from
the universe or something. Yeah. Synchronicities.
I don't know. I love that humans are always
discovering more about ourselves as we,
you know, heal ourselves. We're really learning
and remembering who we really are. You know,
it's as we're as we're learning more, we're
almost unlearning and remembering who who we
already. Speaker 1 Are that way seems that way.
Yeah, yeah. Still mysterious, still frustrating.
You know, I still don't know how I'm going to pay
my bills this month, but you and me both. Rather.
It's been quite a ride though, so. Speaker 2 Yeah,
yeah, yeah, we're all just walking each other
home. Speaker 1 I hope so, we're going somewhere.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Speaker 2 All right, Mr. Sean
Blackwell. Well, I would love to just give you one
more opportunity. If there's anything that is at
the edge of your mind or something that we didn't
mention that you kind of wanted to bring up, any,
you know, bows to tie anything like that. I just
wanted to give you that opportunity or anything
that you would like to leave the guests with.
Speaker 1 Oh, man. I think it's been a terrific
conversation. I think we've pretty much said all
that needs to be said on this. Obviously, you and
I could go back and forth for another 10 or 20 or
200 hours. Speaker 2 Easily 100%. Speaker 1 Yeah.
But, yeah, if anyone's interested in my work, you
can access everything at Bipolar awakenings.com.
Both books are free PDFs there. There's a link
to my YouTube channel. You know, the whole bit.
Okay. Speaker 2 Yeah, yeah. Listeners, you'll
check out those links below if you want to check
out some more. Sean, you have everything you need,
down below. And, and if you, if you write more or
you work on some more projects in the past
and you'd like to have another conversation,
I would love to have you any time, Sean.
Speaker 2 So please just reach out anytime,
buddy. Speaker 1 Wow. That's great. And if I'm
in Austin, I'll definitely look you up. Yeah,
that would be excellent. Excellent. Speaker
2 All right, man. Well, hey, I'm wishing
you the best. Thank you again so much for your
time. I hope you have a good rest of your day,
listeners. You know the drill. What I always say
at the end of every episode, drink some water,
stretch. Love yourself, slow down. And,
subscribe. We'll see you next episode.